Finding Aid for Ferry Family (William Montague Ferry family) Papers 1823-1904
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ferry Family Papers (William Montague Ferry family) 1823-1904
Ferry Family (William Montague Ferry family)
851272 Aa 2; Ac
William Montague Ferry served as missionary to Indians at Michilimackinac, Michigan for the United Foreign Missionary Society, 1822-1834 and as clergyman in Grand Haven, Michigan. William Montague Ferry, Jr. served in the 14th Michigan Infantry in the Civil War, as University of Michigan Regent and later moved to Park City, Utah where he was active in Democratic Party politics. Thomas W. Ferry served as congressman, 1865 to 1871, and as U.S. Senator from 1871 to 1883. Papers include correspondence describing missionary work of William M. Ferry, Sr., civil war letters of William M. Ferry, Jr., some political correspondence of Thomas W. Ferry, and letters of Amanda White Ferry, wife of William Sr.
0.8 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Civil War correspondence of William M. Ferry, Jr. was donated by Mr. M.A. Anderson (donor no. 3766 ) in 1961. The remainder of the collection was donated in 1938 and 1939 by Miss Hollister Hancock (donor no. 856 ), granddaughter of William M. Ferry.
The collection is open for research.
William Montague Ferry was born September 8, 1796 in Granby, Massachusetts. After training and study to become a member of the clergy, Ferry was licensed and ordained by the Presbytery of New York in 1822. He then offered his services to the United Foreign Missionary Society, and was subsequently appointed to explore and preach among the Indian tribes of the northwest. The result of this exploration was the establishment of, and Ferry's appointment to, the Mackinac mission on Michilimackinac. Ferry worked among the Indians for more than a decade, then because of failing health, he moved downstate to Ottawa County, arriving in 1834. For the remainder of this life, he was a clergyman in Grand Haven, also for a time postmaster of the city. In 1823, he had married Amanda White. Ferry died in 1868.
William Montague Ferry, Jr. was born to the Rev. William Montague and Amanda (White) Ferry on July 8, 1824, in Michilimackinac, Michigan. Ten years later his family moved to Grand Haven, Michigan, where Ferry resided for over forty years. His academic training began under his father and continued with one year at Sanderson Academy in Ashfield, Massachusetts, followed by a year at the University of Michigan's Kalamazoo branch. Ferry served as a regent of the University of Michigan from 1858 to 1863. In August of 1861 he enlisted in the 14th Michigan Infantry, being honorably mustered out in April 24, 1865. He ran unsuccessfully for governor of Michigan in 1870 on the Democratic ticket. He was later appointed by the governor to be a member of a commission to revise the state constitution. He was elected mayor of Grand Rapids in 1876, but then moved to Park City, Utah, in 1878 where he became actively involved in the territory's mining operations. He represented Utah on the National Democratic Committee from 1884 to 1892, and in 1893 was commissioner of the World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago. In 1904 he was nominated on the American ticket to be governor of Utah. He was also a member of the Society of the Army of the Tennessee and of the Military Order of the Loyal Legion. Ferry married Jeannette Hollister of Grand Rapids, Michigan, on October 29, 1851; they had six children. Ferry died January 2, 1905, at Park City, Utah, and was buried in Grand Haven.
Thomas W. Ferry, the younger brother of William Montague Ferry, Jr., was born June 1, 1827, in Michilimackinac, Michigan. Educated in the public schools, Thomas Ferry served as a representative to the state legislature from Kent and Ottawa counties in 1851. He was also a senator from the thirty-first district during the 1887/88 year, a member of Congress from 1865 to 1871, and a U.S. Senator from 1871 to 1883. While in the House, Ferry was chairman of the sub-committee on the New York Post Office building. While in the Senate, he was elected president pro tem and became acting vice-president upon the death of Vice-President Wilson, a position he held until March 4, 1877. As a senator Ferry was chairman of the committees on rules, post offices, and post-roads, and a member of the committee on finance. He presided over the impeachment trial of Secretary of War Belknap and at the joint convention of the 1877 electoral count. Although a leading candidate for re-election in 1883, his name was withdrawn from the candidacy after a long and heated contest. Thomas W. Ferry died in October of 1896 in Grand Haven, Michigan.
The William Montague Ferry family papers have been arranged in two series: Individual Family Members and Ferry Family. The first includes files for William and Amanda Ferry, William Montague Ferry, William Montague Ferry, Jr., and Thomas White Ferry. The latter includes material spanning several family members.
The Ferry family collection consists of letters and typescripts of letters from William Montague Ferry and his wife Amanda White Ferry describing their trip from Ashfield, Massachusetts, to Mackinac Island and their missionary work among the Indians; letters, 1862-1901, of Colonel William M. Ferry, University of Michigan regent, particularly to his wife and other relatives while serving in the Fourteenth Michigan Infantry during the Civil War; speeches and letters from contemporary politicians to Thomas White Ferry, lumberman and U.S. Senator; and two scrapbooks of newspaper clippings on the Ferry family. Correspondents in the collection include: Susan B. Anthony, Henry P. Baldwin, Zachariah Chandler, Schuyler Colfax, William M. Evarts, Hamilton Fish, Rutherford B. Haye, Whitelaw Reid, and Elizabeth Cady Stanton
Subjects:
Ferry family.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 14th (1862-1865); Indians of North America--Missions--Michigan.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Missionaries--Michigan--Mackinac Island.; Women travelers--Suffrage--Michigan.; Women's rights--Michigan.; Women in missionary work--Michigan--Mackinac Island.; Ashfield (Mass.); Grand Haven (Mich.); Mackinac Island (Mich.); Michigan--Description and travel.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Sermons.
Contributors:
Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906.; Baldwin, Henry P. (Henry Porter), 1814-1892.; Chandler, Zachariah, 1813-1879.; Colfax, Schuyler, 1823-1885.; Evarts, William Maxwell, 1818-1901.; Ferry, Amanda White.; Ferry, Thomas White, 1827-1896.; Ferry, William Montague, 1796-1867.; Ferry, William Montague, 1824-1905.; Fish, Hamilton, 1888-1991; Hayes, Rutherford Birchard, 1822-1893.; Reid, Whitelaw, 1837-1912.; Stanton, Elizabeth Cady, 1815-1902.
Genre/Form:
Sermons.; Scrapbooks.
- Family papers
  - William and Amanda Ferry: Typed excerpts from selected letters written from Mackinac Island 1823-1834 (Box 1)
  - Amanda White Ferry letters 1823-1838 (Box 1)
  - William M. Ferry
    - Letters 1860, 1865 (Box 1)
    - Last will and testament 1867 (Box 1)
    - Estate papers: probate file 1868 (Box 1)
    - In Memoriam....William M. Ferry 1869 (Box 1)
  - William Montague Ferry, Jr.
    - Civil War letters
      - 1861-1862 (Box 1)
      - January-March 1863 (Box 1)
      - April-July 1863 (Box 1)
      - August 1863-February 1864 (Box 1)
      - March-May 1864 (Box 1)
      - June-August 1864 (Box 1)
      - September 1864; December 1864, February 1865 (Box 1)
    - Other correspondence and papers
      - 1872-1895 (Box 1)
      - 1896-1899 (Box 1)
      - 1900-1904 (Box 1)
      - 1861 1873 (Folder 1)
    - Biographical and historical information, including speech given before Old Settler's banquet 1897 (Box 1)
  - Thomas White Ferry:
    - Correspondence 1869-1881, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous invitations, etc. 1865-1883 (Box 1)
  - Ferry Family
    - Miscellaneous 1849-1893, undated (scattered) (Box 1)
      (includes copy of letter from Abraham Lincoln to Amanda Hale, 1865)
    - Scrapbook containing news clippings of obituaries, local history clippings, etc. undated (mid to late 19th century), 2 volumes (Box 1)
    - Loose clippings from scrapbook (Box 1)